Guide to the Angna Enters and Louis Kalonyme Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Angna Enters and Louis Kalonyme papers
1919-1960
YCAL MSS 430
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.97
(10 boxes) + 3 art objects + 5 broadside folders
The Angna Enters and Louis Kalonyme papers contain artwork, correspondence, and printed material documenting the life and work of artist Angna Enters and her husband, art critic and journalist, Louis Kalonyme. The collection features over 70 pieces of original artwork by Enters dating chiefly from the 1930s and 1940s. Correspondents include fellow artists and friends John Marin, Alfred Stieglitz, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill. Other materials include photographs of Kalonyme, O'Keeffe, Stieglitz, and Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill, and a scrapbook and clippings of Kalonyme's writings for newspapers.
Enters, Angna, 1897-1989
Kalonyme, Louis
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Jason C. Berger, 1990 to 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Agna Enters Papers, (S)*MGZMD 158, Jerome Robbins Dance Division, The New York Public Library for the Performing Arts.
Angna Enters (1907-1989) and Louis Kalonyme (d. 1961)
Angna Enters, born Anita Irene Enters in New York City to Edward and Henriette (Gasseur-Styleau) Enters, was a performer, artist, lecturer, and author. Enters studied ballet in Milwaukee, where the family relocated in 1914, before returning to New York, where she studied dance with Michio Ito and painting at the Art Students' League. Enters gained recognition in the 1920s for her distinctive stage performances combining dance and mime, and from 1928 to 1960 she played approximately three hundred characters in her traveling Theater of Angna Enters; Enters was responsible for nearly all aspects of her theater, from making costumes and props to composing music. She was also a sculptor and painter, exhibiting work in New York and London. In the 1950s Enters began lecturing at universities, and in the early 1960s she served as an artist in residence at Dallas Theater Center and Baylor University. Among her writings are the stage works "Love Possessed Juana: A Play of the Inquisition in Spain" and "The Unknown Lover," the novel Among the Daughters (1955), and the autobiographies First Person Plural (1937), Silly Girl (1944), and Artist's Life (1958).
Louis Kalonyme, born Louis Kanter, was an art critic and journalist. Kalonyme and Enters met in 1921 and married in 1934.
Biographical information taken from "Angna Enters." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2003. Gale Biography In Context (accessed 5 January 2011).
Scope and Contents
The Angna Enters and Louis Kalonyme papers contain artwork, correspondence, and printed material documenting the life and work of artist Angna Enters and her husband Louis Kalonyme. The collection features over 70 pieces of original artwork by Enters dating chiefly from the 1930s and 1940s. Correspondents include fellow artists and friends John Marin, Alfred Stieglitz, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill. Other materials include photographs and negatives of Kalonyme, O'Keeffe, Stieglitz, and Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill, and a scrapbook and clippings of Kalonyme's writings for newspapers.
Arrangement
Organized chronologically by accession: I. May 1990 Acquisition, 1919-1960. II. December 1999 Acquisition, undated. III. January 2001 Acquisition, 1933-1960.
Artists; Arts, Modern -- 20th Century; Clippings (information artifacts); Pastels (visual works); Photographic prints; Watercolors (paintings); Artists; Enters, Angna, 1897-1989; Kalonyme, Louis; Marin, John, 1870-1953; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986; O'Neill, Carlotta; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946
- May 1990 Acquisition, 1919-1960; 2.97; (5 boxes)
  General note
  Formerly classed as Uncat Za Ms 150.
  Scope and Contents
  The May 1990 Gift contains correspondence and printed material by, to, or relating to Angna Enters and Louis (Kantor) Kalonyme. Correspondents include John Marin, Georgia O'Keeffe, Agnes O'Neill, Carlotta O'Neill, Eugene O'Neill, and Alfred Stieglitz. Other materials include a scrapbook and clippings of Kalonyme's writings for newspapers.
  - Preliminary list, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Stieglitz to Kalonyme, 1926-1940; 4 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence O'Keeffe to Kalonyme, 1931-1933; 2 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence O'Keeffe to Kalonyme, Kalonyme to O'Keeffe, 1934-1959; 2 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence O'Neill to Kalonyme, 1921-1928 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence O'Neill and Monterey to Kalonyme, 1928-1929; 2 (Box 2)
    Includes photographic negatives
  - Correspondence O'Neill to Kalonyme, 1929-1932; 2 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence Marin to Kalonyme, Kalonyme to Marin, Marin to O'Keeffe, 1939-1950; 2 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence Marin to Kalonyme, 1953 July 27 (Box 3)
  - Christmas card and etching from Marin to Kalonyme, 1941-1943 (Box 3)
  - Printed program of a meeting at which the Nazi Party declared itself. Kalonyme attended as a correspondent, 1923 September 1 (Box 3)
  - Master copy of the play "Chantecler", 1960 (Box 3)
  - Copy of the script from O'Neill's play "Lazarus Laughed", undated (Box 3)
  - "Investigation and inquiry into allegations of cruelty...", 1920 March 9 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1925-1928 (Box 5 Oversize)
  - Newspaper clippings of Kalonyme's writings, [1919-1928] (Box 6 Oversize)
- December 1999 Acquisition, undated; 0.11; (9 folders)
  Formerly classed as Uncat Za Ms 644.
  The December 1999 Gift contains photographs and negatives of Georgia O'Keeffe, Alfred Stieglitz, Louis Kalonyme, Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill, and other related subjects.
  - Photographs and negatives, undated; 9 (Box 3)
    Includes photographs by Alfred Stieglitz
- January 2001 Acquisition, 1933-1960; 6.89; (5 boxes) + 3 art objects, 5 broadside folders
  Formerly classed as Uncat Mss 107.
  The January 2001 Gift consists of original artwork by Angna Enters, including watercolor, oil, and pastel works. The works date chiefly from 1933 through the late 1940s.
  - "Drawings from [Greek] Vases," ink on paper, approx. 10 x 16", 1934; 3 (Box 4)
  - Park scene, watercolor on paper, approx. 8 x 10", undated (Box 4)
  - Girls in park with ball, watercolor on paper, approx. 8 x 10", 1942 (Box 4)
  - "Primrose," pencil and watercolor on paper, approx. 7 x 6", undated (Box 4)
  - Seascape, watercolor on paper, approx. 8 x 10", 1934 (Box 4)
  - Seascape with green rocks and white boat, watercolor or tempera on paper, approx. 8 x 10", 1934 (Box 4)
  - Village rooftops, watercolor on paper, approx. 8 x 10", 1934 (Box 4)
  - Harbor with boats against town, pencil, approx. 12 x 15", undated (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Couple on a veranda, pastel, approx. 16 x 20", 1947 (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Village with bride and church, watercolor, approx. 14 x 20", 1933 (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Moroccan scene, man and two women, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Moroccan men smoking, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", 1942 (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Moroccan scene, rooftops with people, [1933?] (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Village in desert with man on horseback and man walking, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Woman in black with baby, watercolor, approx. 12 x 15", matted, undated (Box 7 Oversize)
  - "Karnak," watercolor, approx. 12 x 15", matted, 1935 (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Moroccan scene with tower, watercolor, approx. 12 x 15", matted, 1933 (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Town with two tall structures, watercolor, approx. 15 x 20", matted, 1933 (Box 7 Oversize)
  - Village with bridge and rainbow, watercolor, approx. 15 x 20", 1933-1934, undated (Box 7 Oversize)
    Includes two other watercolors
  - Abstract scene with eye, watercolor, approx. 12 x 15", 1934 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Harbor with boats against town, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", 1934 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Waterscape with sailboat, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", 1935 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Moroccan men in groups, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Hillside landscape in greens and purples, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", 1946 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Bouquet of flowers, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", 1941 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Beach scene of 1910 images, watercolor on paper on board, approx. 16 x 20", 1946 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Village, pencil, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Urban landscape, pencil, approx. 12 x 15", undated (Box 8 Oversize)
  - French café scene, pastel, approx. 16 x 20", 1943 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Park scene on green paper, pastel, approx. 13 x 17", undated (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Park scene with children, woman on bench, horses, pastel, approx. 16 x 20", 1946 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - "Cretan shepherd," "Athenian Citizen Selling Beads," "Cretan Woman," watercolors on paper, approx. 8 x 10", 1934 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - Landscape with church and fall leaves, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", 1943 (Box 8 Oversize)
  - "Praha" (interior), watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", 1933 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Landscape with person in red, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 9 Oversize)
  - View of town and harbor, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", 1933 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Park scene with woman and man on chairs, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", 1938 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Park scene with empty chairs, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 9 Oversize)
  - "Service," man at table, watercolor on paper, approx. 12 x 18", 1943 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Couple at table in restaurant, watercolor or tempera on paper, approx. 16 x 20", undated (Box 9 Oversize)
  - "Place Massen," town square, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", 1944 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Houses among hills, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 20", 1948 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Park scene with man on chair, watercolor on paper, approx. 14 x 16", undated (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Park scene with empty chairs, watercolor on paper, approx. 14 x 16", 1960 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Square (in Paris)?, watercolor on paper, approx. 14 x 16", undated (Box 9 Oversize)
  - New York Harbor, watercolor on paper, approx. 14 x 16", undated (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Abstract ships with American flag, watercolor on paper, approx. 14 x 16", 1935 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - "Richmond Park-London," watercolor on paper, approx. 18 x 22", 1940 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - Vase of lilacs, oil on board, approx. 12 x 16", 1950 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - "K'rem Long," ink drawing of flute player on paper, approx. 9 x 12", framed, undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Three children, pastel on paper, approx. 9 x 12", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Park, watercolor on paper, approx. 9 x 12", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - People at tables in park, pencil and watercolor on paper, approx. 9 x 12", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Village with church, dark sky, watercolor on paper, approx. 9 x 12", 1933 (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Onion-domed churches, watercolor on paper, approx. 9 x 12", 1935 (Box 10 Oversize)
  - "Salvia," watercolor on cardboard, approx. 7 x 15", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - "Spray of white flowers," watercolor on cardboard, approx. 7 x 15", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - "Larkspur," watercolor on cardboard, approx. 10 x 15", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - "Thistle," watercolor on cardboard, approx. 10 x 15", undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Harbor with rocks and boat, watercolor on paper, approx. 9 x 12", 1934 (Box 10 Oversize)
  - "Green Hour," oil on canvas, approx. 26 x 32", undated (Box 11 Artstorage)
  - "Pierrot," tempera (?) approx. 20 x 26", undated (Box 12 Artstorage)
  - "Carol Levin," pencil and pastel on paper, approx. 8 x 10", undated (Box 13 Artstorage)
  - Spanish or Moroccan scene with soldier and two women, watercolor on paper, approx. 16 x 22", matted, undated (Box 14 Broadside)
  - Portrait of Millie Lewin, pastel on paper on board, approx. 20 x 30", 1949 (Box 15 Broadside)
  - Castle in distance, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", matted, 1933 (Box 16 Broadside)
  - "Tetouam," men in Moroccan setting, watercolor, approx. 16 x 20", matted, 1933 (Box 17 Broadside)
  - Interior with woman playing piano, pastel, approx. 28 x 24", 1944 (Box 18 Broadside)
  - Landscape in greens and purples, watercolor, approx. 28 x 24", 1945 (Box 18 Broadside)
  - Three women at a bar, pastel, approx. 28 x 24", 1946 (Box 18 Broadside)
  - Three women in long dresses before a mansion, watercolor, approx. 28 x 24", undated (Box 18 Broadside)